Well, this is a really extraordinary honor for me. I spend most of my time in jails and
prisons on death row. I spend most of my time in very low-income communities and the projects
and places where there's a great deal of hopelessness. And being here at TED and seeing the stimulation,
hearing it has been very, very energizing to me. And one of the things that's emerged
in my short time here is that TED has an identity. And you can actually say things here that
have impacts around the world. And sometimes when it comes through TED, it has meaning
and power that it doesn't have when it doesn't. And I mention that because I think identity
is really important. And we've had some fantastic presentations. And I think what we've learned
is that if you're a teacher, your words can be meaningful, but if you're a compassionate
teacher, they can be especially meaningful. If you're a doctor, you can do some good things,
but if you're a caring doctor, you can do some other things. So I want to talk about
the power of identity. And I didn't learn about this actually practicing law and doing
the work that I do. I actually learned about this from my grandmother. I grew up in a house
that was the traditional African American home that was dominated by a matriarch, and
that matriarch was my grandmother. She was tough. She was strong. She was powerful. She
was the end of every argument in our family. She was the beginning of a lot of arguments
in our family. She was the daughter of people who were actually enslaved. Her parents were
born in slavery in Virginia in the 1840s. She was born in the 1880s, and the experience
of slavery very much shaped the way she saw the world. My grandmother was tough, but she
was also loving. When I would see her as a little boy, she'd come up to me, and she'd
give me these hugs, and she'd squeeze me so tight I could barely breathe. And then she'd
let me go. And an hour or two later, if I saw her, she'd come over to me, and she'd
say, Brian, do you still feel me hugging you? And if I said no, she'd assault me again,
and if I'd say yes, she'd leave me alone. And she just had this quality that you always
wanted to be near her. And the only challenge was that she had 10 children. My mom was the
youngest of her 10 kids, and sometimes when I would go and spend time with her, it would
be difficult to get her time and attention. My cousins would be running around everywhere.
And I remember when I was about 8 or 9 years old, waking up one morning, going into the
living room, and all of my cousins were running around, and my grandmother was sitting across
the room staring at me. And at first I thought we were playing a game. And I would look at
her, and I'd smile, but she was very serious. And after about 15 or 20 minutes of this,
she got up and she came across the room, and she took me by the hand, and she said, come
on, Brian, you and I are going to have a talk. And I remember this just like it happened
yesterday. I never will forget it. She took me out back, and she said, Brian, I'm going
to tell you something, but you don't tell anybody what I tell you. I said, okay, mom.
And she said, now you make sure you don't do that. I said, sure. Then she sat me down,
and she looked at me, and she said, I want you to know I've been watching you. And she
said, I think you're special. She said, I think you can do anything you want to do.
I will never forget it. And then she said, I just need you to promise me three things,
Brian. I said, okay, mom. And she said, the first thing I want you to promise me is that
you'll always love your mom. She said, that's my baby girl, and you have to promise me now
you'll always take care of her. Well, I adored my mom, so I said, yes, mama, I'll do that.
Then she said, the second thing I want you to promise me is that you'll always do the
right thing, even when the right thing is the hard thing. And I thought about it, and
I said, yes, mama, I'll do that. Then finally she said, the third thing I want you to promise
me is that you'll never drink alcohol. Well, I was nine years old, so I said, yes, mama,
I'll do that. I grew up in the country in the rural south, and I have a brother a year
older than me and a sister a year younger. When I was about 14 or 15, one day my brother
came home, and he had this six-pack of beer. I don't know where he got it. And he grabbed
me and my sister, and we went out in the woods, and we were kind of just out there doing the
stuff we crazily did. And he had a sip of this beer, and he gave some to my sister,
and she had some, and they offered it to me. I said, no, no, no, no, that's okay, y'all
go ahead. I'm not going to have any beer. And my brother said, come on, we're doing
this today. You always do what we do. I had some, your sister had some, have some beer.
I said, no, I don't feel right about that. Y'all go ahead, y'all go ahead. And then my
brother started staring at me. He said, what's wrong with you? Have some beer. Then he looked
at me real hard. He said, oh, I hope you're not still hung up on that conversation Mama
had with you. I said, well, what are you talking about? He says, oh, Mama tells all the grandkids
that they're special. I was devastated. And I'm going to admit something to you. I'm going
to tell you something I probably shouldn't. I know this might be broadcast broadly, but
I'm 52 years old and I'm going to admit to you that I've never had a drop of alcohol.
I don't say that because I think that's virtuous. I say that because there is power in identity.
When we create the right kind of identity, we can say things to the world around us that
they don't actually believe make sense. We can get them to do things that they don't
think they can do. When I thought about my grandmother, of course she would think all
her grandkids were special. My grandfather was in prison during prohibition. My male
uncles died of alcohol-related diseases. And these were the things she thought we needed
to commit to. Well, I've been trying to say something about our criminal justice system.
This country is very different today than it was 40 years ago. In 1972, there were 300,000
people in jails and prisons. Today, there are 2.3 million. The United States now has
the highest rate of incarceration in the world. We have 7 million people on probation
and parole. And mass incarceration, in my judgment, has fundamentally changed our world.
In poor communities and communities of color, there is this despair, there is this hopelessness
that is being shaped by these outcomes. One out of three black men between the ages of
18 and 30 is in jail, in prison, on probation or parole. In urban communities across this
country, Los Angeles, Philadelphia, Baltimore, Washington, 50 to 60 percent of all young
men of color in jail or prison, or on probation and parole. Our system isn't just being shaped
in these ways that seem to be distorting around race, they're also distorted by poverty. We
have a system of justice in this country that treats you much better if you're rich and
guilty than if you're poor and innocent. Wealth, not culpability, shapes outcomes. And yet
we seem to be very comfortable. The politics of fear and anger has made us believe that
these are problems that are not our problems. We've been disconnected. It's interesting
to me, we're looking at some very interesting developments in our work. My state of Alabama,
like a number of states, actually permanently disenfranchises you if you have a criminal
conviction. Right now in Alabama, 34 percent of the black male population has permanently
lost the right to vote. We're actually projecting in another 10 years the level of disenfranchisement
will be as high as it's been since prior to the passage of the Voting Rights Act and
there is this stunning silence. I represent children. A lot of my clients are very young.
The United States is the only country in the world where we sentence 13-year-old children
to die in prison. We have life imprisonment without parole for kids in this country. We're
actually doing some litigation. The only country in the world. I represent people on
death row. It's interesting, this question of the death penalty. In many ways, we've
been taught to think that the real question is, do people deserve to die for the crimes
they've committed? And that's a very sensible question. But there's another way of thinking
about where we are in our identity. The other way of thinking about it is not do people
deserve to die for the crimes they commit, but do we deserve to kill? I mean, it's fascinating.
Death penalty in America is defined by error. For every nine people who have been executed,
we've actually identified one innocent person who's been exonerated and released from death
row. A kind of astonishing error rate. One out of nine people. Innocent. I mean, it's
fascinating in aviation, we would never let people fly on airplanes if for every nine
planes that took off, one would crash. But somehow we can insulate ourselves from this
problem. It's not our problem. It's not our burden. It's not our struggle. Well, I talk
a lot about these issues. I talk about race and this question of whether we deserve to
kill. And it's interesting, when I teach my students about African American history, I
tell them about slavery. I tell them about terrorism, the era that began at the end of
Reconstruction that went on to World War II. We don't really know very much about it, but
for African Americans in this country, that was an error defined by terror. In many communities,
people had to worry about being lynched. They had to worry about being bombed. It was the
threat of terror that shaped their lives. And these older people come up to me now and
they say, Mr. Stevenson, you give talks, you make speeches. You tell people to stop saying
we're dealing with terrorism for the first time in our nation's history after 9-11. They
tell me to say, no, tell them that we grew up with that. And that era of terrorism, of
course, was followed by segregation and decades of racial subordination and apartheid. And
yet we have in this country this dynamic where we really don't like to talk about our problems.
We don't like to talk about our history. And because of that, we really haven't understood
what it's meant to do the things we've done historically. We're constantly running into
each other. We're constantly creating tensions and conflicts. We have a hard time talking
about race. And I believe it's because we are unwilling to commit ourselves to a process
of truth and reconciliation. In South Africa, people understood that we couldn't overcome
apartheid without a commitment to truth and reconciliation. In Rwanda, even after the
genocide, there was this commitment. But in this country we haven't done that. I was giving
this lecture in Germany, some lectures in Germany about the death penalty. It was fascinating
because one of the scholars stood up after the presentation and said, well, you know,
it's deeply troubling to hear what you're talking about. I said, well, we don't have
the death penalty in Germany. And of course, we can never have the death penalty in Germany.
And the room got very quiet and this woman said, there's no way with our history we can
ever engage in the systematic killing of human beings. It would be unconscionable for us
to in an intentional, deliberate way set about executing people. And I thought about that.
What would it feel like to be living in a world where the nation state of Germany was
executing people, especially if they were disproportionately Jewish? I couldn't bear
it. It would be unconscionable. And yet in this country, in the states of the old south,
we execute people where you're 11 times more likely to get the death penalty if the victim
is white than if the victim is black, 22 times more likely to get it if the defendant
is black and the victim is white. In the very states where there are buried in the ground
the bodies of people who were lynched. And yet there is this disconnect. Well, I believe
that our identity is at risk. That when we actually don't care about these difficult
things, the positive and wonderful things are nonetheless implicated. We love innovation.
We love technology. We love creativity. We love entertainment. But ultimately those realities
are shadowed by suffering, abuse, degradation, marginalization. And for me, it becomes necessary
to integrate the two. Because ultimately we are talking about a need to be more hopeful,
more committed, more dedicated to the basic challenges of living in a complex world. And
for that means, for me that means spending time thinking and talking about the poor,
the disadvantaged, those who will never get to TED. But thinking about them in a way that
is integrated in our own lives. You know, ultimately we all have to believe things we
haven't seen. We do. As rational as we are, as committed to intellect as we are, innovation,
creativity, development comes not from the ideas in our mind alone. They come from the
ideas in our mind that are also fueled by some conviction in our heart. And it's that
mind-heart connection that I believe compels us to not just be attentive to all the bright
and dazzling things, but also the dark and difficult things. Václav Havel, the great
Czech leader, talked about this. He said, when we were in Eastern Europe and dealing
with oppression, we wanted all kinds of things, but mostly what we needed was hope, an orientation
of the spirit, a willingness to sometimes be in hopeless places and be a witness. Well,
that orientation of the spirit is very much at the core of what I believe even TED communities
have to be engaged in. There is no disconnect around technology and design that will allow
us to be fully human until we pay attention to suffering, to poverty, to exclusion, to
unfairness, to injustice. Now, I will warn you that this kind of identity is a much more
challenging identity than ones that don't pay attention to this. It will get to you.
I had the great privilege when I was a young lawyer meeting Rosa Parks, and Ms. Parks used
to come back to Montgomery every now and then, and she would get together with two of her
dearest friends, these older women, Johnny Carr, who was the organizer of the Montgomery
Bus Boycott, an amazing African American woman, and Virginia Durr, a white woman, whose husband
Clifford Durr represented Dr. King. And these women would get together and just talk. And
every now and then Ms. Carr would call me, and she'd say, Brian, Ms. Parks is coming
to town, and we're going to get together and talk. Do you want to come over and listen?
And I'd say, yes, ma'am, I do. And she said, well, what are you going to do when you get
here? I said, I'm going to listen. And I'd go over there, and I would. I would just listen.
It would be so energizing and so empowering. And one time I was over there listening to
these women talk, and after a couple of hours, Ms. Parks turned to me, and she said, now,
Brian, tell me what the Equal Justice Initiative is. Tell me what you're trying to do. I began
giving her my wrap. I said, well, we're trying to challenge injustice. We're trying to help
people who have been wrongly convicted. We're trying to confront bias and discrimination
in the administration of criminal justice. We're trying to end a life without parole
sentences for children. We're trying to do something about the death penalty. We're trying
to reduce the prison population. We're trying to end mass incarceration. I gave her my whole
wrap, and when I finished, she looked at me, and she said, mm, mm, mm. She said, that's
going to make you tired, tired, tired. And that's when Ms. Carr leaned forward. She put
her finger on my face, and she said, that's why you've got to be brave, brave, brave.
And I actually believe that the TED community needs to be more courageous. We need to find
ways to embrace these challenges, these problems, the suffering, because ultimately, our humanity
depends on everyone's humanity. I've learned very simple things doing the work that I do.
It's just taught me very simple things. I've come to understand and to believe that each
of us is more than the worst thing we've ever done. I believe that for every person on the
planet, I think if somebody tells a lie, they're not just a liar. I think if somebody takes
something that doesn't belong to them, they're not just a thief. I think even if you kill
someone, you're not just a killer. And because of that, there's this basic human dignity
that must be respected by law. I also believe that in many parts of this country, and certainly
in many parts of this globe, that the opposite of poverty is not wealth. I don't believe
it. I actually think in too many places, the opposite of poverty is justice. And finally,
I believe that despite the fact that it is so dramatic and so beautiful and so inspiring
and so stimulating, we will ultimately not be judged by our technology. We won't be judged
by our design. We won't be judged by our intellect and reason. Ultimately, you judge the character
of a society, not by how they treat the rich and the powerful and the privileged, but by
how they treat the poor, the condemned, the incarcerated, because it's in that nexus that
we actually begin to understand truly profound things about who we are. I sometimes get out
of balance. I'll end with this story. I sometimes push too hard. I do get tired, as we all do.
Sometimes those ideas get ahead of our thinking in ways that are important. And I've been
representing these kids who have been sentenced to these very harsh sentences. And I go to
the jail, and I see my client who's 13 and 14, and he's been certified to stand trial
as an adult. And I start thinking, well, how did that happen? How can a judge turn you
into something that you're not? And the judge has certified him as an adult, but I see this
kid, and I was up too late one night, and I started thinking, well, gosh, if the judge
can turn you into something that you're not, the judge must have magic power. I said, yeah,
Brian, the judge has some magic power. You should ask for some of that. And because I
was up too late and wasn't thinking real straight, I started working on a motion. And
I had a client who was 14 years old, a young, poor, black kid, and started working on this
motion, and the head of the motion was a motion to try my poor 14-year-old black male client
like a privileged white 75-year-old corporate executive. And I put in my motion that there
was prosecutorial misconduct and police misconduct and judicial misconduct. There was a crazy
line in there about how there's no conduct in this county, it's all misconduct. And the
next morning, I woke up, and I thought, now, did I dream that crazy motion, or did I actually
write it? And to my horror, not only had I written it, but I had sent it to court. A
couple months went by, and I just had forgotten all about it. And I finally decided, oh, gosh,
I've got to go to the court and do this crazy case. And I got in my car, and I was feeling
really overwhelmed, overwhelmed. And I got in my car, and I went to this courthouse,
and I was sitting, oh, this is going to be so difficult, so painful. And I finally got
out of the car, and I started walking up to the courthouse. And as I was walking up the
steps of this courthouse, there was an older black man who was the janitor in this courthouse.
And when this man saw me, he came over to me, and he said, who are you? I said, I'm
a lawyer. He said, you're a lawyer? I said, yes, sir. And this man came over to me, and
he hugged me. And he whispered in my ear, he said, I'm so proud of you. And I have to
tell you, it was energizing. It connected deeply with something in me about identity,
about the capacity of every person to contribute to community, to perspective that is hopeful.
Well, I went into the courtroom. As soon as I walked inside, the judge saw me coming in.
He said, Mr. Stevenson, did you write this crazy motion? I said, yes, sir, I did. And
we started arguing. People started coming in because they were just outraged. I'd written
these crazy things. And police officers were coming in, and assistant prosecutors and clerk
workers. And before I knew it, the courtroom was filled with people angry that we were
talking about race, that we were talking about poverty, that we were talking about inequality.
And out of the corner of my eye, I could see this janitor pacing back and forth. And he
kept looking through the window, and he could hear all of this hollering. He kept pacing
back and forth. And finally, this older black man with this very worried look on his face
came into the courtroom and sat down behind me, almost at counsel table. About 10 minutes
later, the judge said we would take a break. And during the break, there was a deputy sheriff
who was offended that the janitor had come into court. And this deputy jumped up, and
he ran over to this older black man. He said, Jimmy, what are you doing in this courtroom?
This older black man stood up, and he looked at that deputy, and he looked at me. And he
said, I came into this courtroom to tell this young man, keep your eyes on the prize. Hold
on. I've come to TED because I believe that many of you understand that the moral arc
of the universe is long, but it bends toward justice, that we cannot be full, evolved human
beings until we care about human rights and basic dignity, that all of our survival is
tied to the survival of everyone, that our visions of technology and design and entertainment
and creativity have to be married with visions of humanity, compassion, and justice. And
more than anything, for those of you who share that, I've simply come to tell you
that to keep your eyes on the prize, hold on. Thank you very much.
So you heard and saw an obvious desire by this audience, this community, to help you
on your way and to do something on this issue. Other than writing a check, what could we
do? Well, there are opportunities all around us. If you live in the state of California,
for example, there is a referendum coming up this spring where actually there's going
to be an effort to redirect some of the money we spend on the politics of punishment. For
example, here in California, we're going to spend $1 billion on the death penalty in the
next five years. $1 billion. And yet, 46% of all homicide cases don't result in arrests.
56% of all rape cases don't result. So there's an opportunity to change that. And this referendum
would propose having those dollars go to law enforcement and safety. And I think that opportunity
exists all around us. Now, there's been this huge decline in crime
in America over the last three decades. And part of the narrative of that is sometimes
that it's about increased incarceration rates. What would you say to someone who believed
that? Well, actually, the violent crime rate has remained relatively stable. The great
increase in mass incarceration in this country wasn't really in violent crime categories.
It was this misguided war on drugs. That's where the dramatic increases have come in
our prison population. And we got carried away with the rhetoric of punishment. And
so we have three strikes laws that put people in prison forever for stealing a bicycle,
for low-level property crimes, rather than making them give those resources back to the
people who they victimized. I believe we need to do more to help people who are victimized
by crime, not do less. And I think our current punishment philosophy does nothing for no
one. And I think that's the orientation that we have to change.
Brian, you've struck a massive chord here. You're an inspiring person. Thank you so much
for coming today. Thank you very much.
Thank you very much for coming today. Thank you.